Preliminary Guide to the Muriel Henderson Papers, 1900-2009 RL.00531
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Muriel Henderson papers
1900-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Henderson, Muriel, 1920-2009
RL.00531
18 Linear Feet
Muriel Henderson (1920-2009) and her husband, Lawrence (Larry), were originally from Tacoma, Washington. They served as missionaries to Angola from 1947 to 1969 and eventually retired to Durham in the 1990s. The bulk of the papers relate Muriel Henderson's personal and family history (for the Woods and Henderson families). She lived with her husband Lawrence (Larry) Henderson in Angola doing missionary work from 1947 to 1969 and the collection includes many materials from this time (including journals and letters). Henderson kept in touch with people from Angola throughout the remainder of her life. The collection also includes many materials documenting her family's life in the early 20th century in the Pacific Northwest (mostly in or around Tacoma, Washington), including photographs, diaries, children's drawings and letters, school report cards, diplomas, letters, recollections (many typed) from family members, and ledgers of household expenses. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
13500 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Muriel Henderson Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2009.
Biographical Note
Muriel W. Henderson was born on June 20, 1920 in Tacoma, Washington, and died on June 9, 2009 in Chapel Hill, NC. Her family and friends knew her as Ki. She lived a full and active life with a wonderful will to experience as much as possible. She spent 22 years as a missionary in Angola with her husband Larry, leaving there in 1969 when the colonial war for independence made it hard to continue the work. She and Larry moved to New Jersey where he worked for the mission board in New York and she worked in social services. She loved working with African students at the Africa-America Institute. Ki and Larry finished their careers in Florida, first in Leisure City and then at Sun City Center. From 1985 to 1991 they lived in Portugal, where they had first gone in 1947 to learn Portuguese for their work in Angola. Ki helped Larry research in Portuguese archives for his book on the church in Angola. While there, they reconnected with many old friends from Angola. In 1991 they moved to Durham, NC and became active in the life of Pilgrim United Church of Christ. Ki was a life-long letter writer and corresponded with friends and colleagues all over the world.
Biographical sketch taken from Muriel's obituary, available at: http://www.cremationsocietync.com/sitemaker/sites/Cremat2/obit.cgi?user=murial-henderson.
Collection Overview
The bulk of the papers relate to Muriel Henderson's personal and family history (for the Woods and Henderson families). She lived with her husband Lawrence (Larry) Henderson in Angola doing missionary work from 1947 to 1969. The collection includes many materials from this time (including journals and letters), and she kept in touch with people from Angola throughout the remainder of her life. The collection also includes many materials documenting her and her family's life in the early 20th century in the Pacific Northwest (mostly in or around Tacoma, Washington), including photographs, diaries, children's drawings and letters, school report cards, diplomas, letters, recollections (many typed) from family members, and ledgers of household expenses.
Collection Arrangement
The collection has not been processed, but materials have been grouped within each box as best as possible for preservation and ease of use.
Genealogy; Missions -- Angola; Angola; Tacoma (Wash.); Scrapbooks; Henderson, Muriel; Henderson, Muriel, 1920-2009; Henderson, Lawrence
- Accession (2009-0227), 12 boxes and 1 oversize folder
  Scope and Contents note
  The bulk of the papers relate to her personal and family history (for the Woods and Henderson families). She lived with her husband Lawrence (Larry) Henderson in Angola doing missionary work from 1947 to 1969; the collection includes many materials from this time (including journals and letters), and she kept in touch with people from Angola throughout the remainder of her life. The collection also includes many materials documenting her and her family's life in the early 20th century in the Pacific Northwest (mostly in or around Tacoma, Washington), including photographs, diaries, children's drawings and letters, school report cards, diplomas, letters, recollections (many typed) from family members, and ledgers of household expenses.
  - Personal correspondence (Box 1)
  - Diaries (Box 1)
  - Ledger books (Box 1)
  - Diplomas (Box 1)
  - Memory box with letters, early 20th-century photograph, statue, and wood/metal harmonica (Box 1)
  - Court proceedings for a case between her parents and the hospital where their infant son was burned when he rolled into a radiator (Box 1)
  - Personal correspondence (Box 2)
  - Newspapers (Box 2)
  - Binders of family items, including letters, announcements, clippings, children's artwork, etc. (4) (Box 2)
  - Angola mission work (Box 2)
  - Family photographs (Box 3)
  - Correspondence (Box 3)
  - Calendars (Box 3)
  - Personal notes (Box 3)
  - Family letters box, 1922 (Box 3)
  - Other early letters, 1900s-1920s (Box 3)
  - Ralph Woods memorial book (Box 3)
  - Yearbook (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 4)
  - Family photographs (Box 4)
  - Memories folders (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 4)
  - Old passports (Box 4)
  - Notebooks with personal notes and records of letters sent/received (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 4)
  - Family photographs (Box 4)
  - Personal correspondence (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook (Box 6)
  - Personal correspondence (Box 7)
  - Address books (Box 7)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 7)
  - Personal correspondence (Box 8)
  - Newsletters (Box 8)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 8)
  - Christmas cards (Box 9)
  - Address book (Box 9)
  - Photographs, 1940s (Box 9)
  - Report cards (Box 9)
  - Personal correspondence (Box 9)
  - Personal correspondence (Box 10)
  - News clippings (Box 10)
  - Photographs (Box 10)
  - Autograph books, early 20th century (Box 11)
  - Address books (Box 11)
  - Muriel Henderson's baby book (Box 11)
  - Tintype photograph of male relatives (Box 11)
  - Books and diaries (some books discuss family members; most diaries belong to Muriel) (Box 12)
  - Memorial service materials (including a DVD), 2009 (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook pages (Box 12, Oversize-folder 1)